Guide to the William H. Poteat Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
William H. Poteat Papers
1954-2018
RG 243
Yale University Divinity School Library
3
6 boxes
This collection documents the thought and work of William H. Poteat, a Yale Divinity School graduate who taught at Duke University from 1960 to 1987. The material was gathered by Walter B. Mead, who contacted former students and colleagues of Poteat, asking them to provide writings and correspondence of Poteat that document his contributions to the field of philosophy of religion.
Poteat, William H.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Walter B. Mead and others, 2011, 2014, 2015
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
See Box 1, Folder 1 for a more detailed chronology of Poteat's life and work, particularly as it relates to thought of Michael Polanyi.
Chronology
1919 April 19 William Hardman Poteat (WHP) was born in China, the son of Baptist missionaries and a member of a long line of North Carolina educators. He spent the first ten years of his life in China.
1937 Completed his high school education in Raleigh, North Carolina
1941 B.A. degree from Oberlin College with Phi Beta Kappa honors
1944 B.D. Yale Divinity School
1944-1947 Served as a program coordinator for the YMCA at the University of North Carolina – Chapel Hill
1947 Joined the faculty of the Philosophy Department at the University of North Carolina as instructor. Philosophy of Religion was immediately, and would remain throughout his teaching career, a major area of concentration.
1951 Ph.D. Duke University
1955 Having risen to the rank of associate professor at UNC, Poteat received an Outstanding Teaching Award in 1955
1958-1959 Taught at Episcopal Theological Seminary of the Southwest, Austin, TX
1960-1987 Joined Duke University Divinity School faculty as an associate professor of Christianity and Culture
1968-1987 Joined the Department of Religion at Duke University, increasing his role in advising and directing doctoral theses
1968 Poteat and his colleague, Thomas A. Langford, completed their editorial work on Intellect and Hope: Essays in the Thought of Michael Polanyi, published that year by the Duke University Press for the Lilly Endowment Research Program in Christianity and Politics.
1969 Named to the National Humanities Faculty
1972-1978 Chaired the Department of Religion at Duke University
1985 Polanyian Meditations: In Search of a Post-Critical Logic published by the Duke University Press
1987-2000 Professor Emeritus, Duke University
1990 A Philosophical Daybook: Post-Critical Investigations published by the University of Missouri Press
1994 Recovering the Ground: Critical Exercises in Recollection published by the State University of New York Press
1994-1999 Taught in the adult education program at Athens College (a part of the State University of New York system) in Greece, where his wife, Patricia Poteat, served as president, 1994 – 1999
2000 May 17 Died after an extended illness. He was survived by his wife, Patricia; three children, Susan Poteat Uhler; Anne Carlyle; and Edwin McNeill Poteat III; three grandchildren; and his two sisters, Haley McGill and Elizabeth Terry
Scope and Contents
The documentation contained in this collection was gathered from 2009-2014 at the impetus of Walter B. Mead. Mead was a doctoral student in Political Science at Duke University, 1960-1963, at the beginning of Poteat's career at Duke, and he later became greatly influenced by Poteat's writings and a close friend. Mead contacted former students of William Poteat, and others influenced by him, asking them to provide writings and correspondence of Poteat. The collection has been organized according to the contributors of the material, in order to retain information about the varied provenance of the material.
This collection consists of both classroom and public lectures (in both written and audio format) by William H. Poteat, an audio interview of him by one of his students, extensive correspondence between Professor Poteat and his students (and a few who had never taken his courses or seminars), essays and segments of his books in various stages of draft form, his doctoral dissertation, course notes taken by some of his students, and some journalistic clippings relating to Professor Poteat. It also includes reflective observations by those who had conversed with Poteat as readers of his writings, and by those privileged to have had, also, extensive personal contact with him as friends or colleagues, as well as those who participated, between 1968 and 1978 in annual, multi-day, informal, "retreat" symposiums, often traveling from distant parts of the United States in order to reflect upon and extend their earlier learning experiences with him. (These gatherings came to be known as the 'Dutch Creek Falls' symposiums after a location in North Carolina where the group often met. To get a sense of the characteristic conviviality of those who came under the charismatic influence of Professor Poteat, read "A Reflection on the Ethos of the 'Poteat Bunch'," in the file of James W. Stines, the principal symposium convener.) Copies of William H. Poteat's obituaries are also included in this collection; also a complete bibliography of his published writings, a general, chronological outline of his life and career, four brief intellectual biographies of Poteat, and an essay that addresses the question of how his thinking relates to that of his chief mentor, Michael Polanyi.
In order to facilitate an introduction of Professor Poteat to the scholar who comes fairly new to these materials, the following have been pulled from the files of the individual contributors to this collection and placed, together with this present "Description of the William Hardman Poteat Collection," in an introductory section to provide a relatively brief overview of the person and of the significance of his scholarly contributions: a) A Chronology of William H. Poteat's Life and Career; b) The Question of Whether William Poteat is a 'Polanyian'; c) A Bibliography of Poteat's Published Writings; d) Two Brief Intellectual Biographies, by Ronald L. Hall and R. Taylor Scott, Assessing Poteat's Contributions as a Philosopher; e) A Brief Intellectual Biography by James W. Stines, Assessing Poteat's Contributions as a Theologian.
Arrangement
I. Poteat Documentation, 1954-2010
II. Audio Recordings, 1966-2008
III. Writings of Poteat
Philosophy, American -- 20th Century; Poteat, William H.; Polanyi, Michael, 1891-1976
- Poteat Documentation, 1954-2010; Series I
  - Introductory material
    - Essay on "The Question of Whether William Poteat is a 'Polanyian'" (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bibliography of Poteat's Published Writings; Two Brief Intellectual Biographies, by Ronald L. Hall and R. Taylor Scott, Assessing Poteat's Contributions as a Philosopher; A Brief Intellectual Biography by James W. Stines, Assessing Poteat's Contributions as a Theologian (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - List of doctoral dissertations supervised by Poteat, 1962-1985, ca. 1985 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Tributes to Poteat, including "Words of Farewell" by Patricia Lewis Poteat, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Issue of Tradition & Discovery The Polanyi Society Periodical, with papers related to Poteat by several authors, from symposium held at special meeting of Polanyi Society, June 2008 (Volume XXXV Number 2) (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Material contributed by Ellen W. Bernal
    - Handouts from seminars taught by Poteat; footnote from dissertation of Bernal, 1974-1980 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      Scope and Contents
      Including ""Critical Thought and the Project of Merleau-Ponty"; "The Obviousness and Triviality of Polanyi"; "Some Notes Written in the Margins of Michael Polanyi's Personal Knowledge While Reading it for the Umpteenth Time..."
    - Handouts from seminars taught by Poteat, 1971-1975 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Notes from seminars taught by Poteat, 1971-1975 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Seminar papers, 1970-1972 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Bernal's dissertation: "The Meaning of Embodiment in the Thought of Michael Polanyi and Maurice Merleau-Ponty" (William Poteat, supervisor), 1980 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Material contributed by Gus Breytspraak
    - Writings of WHP: "Further Notes in the Margins of Michael Polanyi's Personal Knowledge, January-May, 1976" (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Course-related: "Theology and Art: Religion 81 - A Selected Bibliography" by WHP, ca. 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Material contributed by Dale Cannon
    - Correspondence: WHP to Dale Cannon, 1968-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Writings of WHP: Autobiographical sketch for Duke Divinity School Review; "The Body of Speech: An Essay in Linguistic Metanoia"; "A Few Words About Words", 1964, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Writings of WHP: "Discussion: What is a Poem About?"; "In Search of a Post-Critical Logic: A Prospectus"; Letter to the editor of the Daily News captioned "What Did Goldwater Mean?" (excerpts); "Sixteen Books That Made a Difference: Philosophy and Religion Since WWII"; "Some Notes on the Status of Language in Modernity and the Quarrel of Kierkegaard with Hegel and Danish Hegelianism"; "U.N.C.-Duke Colloquy on Graduate Education - A Position Paper"; "Myths, Stories, History, Eschatology and Action: Some Polanyian Meditations", 1957,1977, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Bibliographies and book reviews by WHP, ca. 1960-1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Course-related: "Contemporary Western Culture"; "Theology and Art" (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - About WHP: "A Reflection on the Ethos of the 'Poteat Bunch'" by James Stines, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Material contributed by Ronald L. Hall
    - "Introduction of Bill Poteat to the Polanyi Society"; book review, reader's report, letter written by Poteat to Hall, 1993, no date (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Material contributed by Richard P. Heitzenrater
    - Bibliography and notes for course on "Theology and Art" - Religion 81, Duke University, no date (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Material contributed by Murray Jardine
    - Correspondence: WHP to/from Houston Craighead; WHP to James Stines, 1987, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Writings of WHP: "Christianity and the European Enlightenment"; "A Commentary"; "Drawing Hands"; "A Few Ontological Left-overs"; "For Whom is the Real Existence of Values a Problem" (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Writings of WHP: "Foundationalism/Anti-Foundationalism"; "The Meaning of Religious Language - Handout"; "Memory and Imagination", 1987, 1989, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Writings of WHP: "Paul Cézanne and the Numinous Power of the Real"; "Persons and Places: Paradigms in Communication"; "Some Reflections on Method"; "Further Reflections on Method"; "A Skeleton Key to Arendt's The Human Condition "; Untitled, re. spirit (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Seminar handout "A Skeleton Key to Arendt's The Human Condition, no date (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Material contributed by Benjamin Ladner
    - Correspondence, including Poteat to/from Ladner, 1968-1993 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Writings of Poteat, including "The Voice of Orpheus"; "Reflections on Walker Percy's Theory of Language", 1968, 1975, no date (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Seminar handout, summer seminar proposal, writings re. Evangelos Moustakas, 1970-1981, no date (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Writings of re. Poteat, including eulogy delivered by Ladner, 1994-2001, no date (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Material contributed by Walter B. Mead
    - Correspondence: WHP to/from Walter B. Mead (WBM), 1988-1995 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence: WHP to/from WBM, 1996-1999 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence: WBM to/from Patricia Poteat (wife of WHP), 1996-2006 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence: WBM and WHP with publishers, 1989-1992 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence: WBM to/from various individuals re. WHP, Polanyi Society, 1994-2008 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Writings of WHP: "Foreknowledge and Foreordination: A Critique of Models of Knowledge"; "Memory and Imagination"; "Prolegomenon"; "Some Remarks on Walter Mead's Essay, 'Poteat's Philosophical Anthropology", 1960, 1997, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - About WHP: News release re. death; memorial service program; "Remembering Bill Poteat" by Ronald L. Hall, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - About WHP: Tradition Discovery: The Polanyi Society Periodical, Volume XXI, No. 1, 1994-1995: Essays on WHP by J. W. Stines, Benjamin Ladner, Bruce Haddox, Dale Cannon, Walter B. Mead, E. M. Adams (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - About WHP: Tradition Discovery: The Polanyi Society Periodical, Volume XXXV, No. 2, 2008-2009: Essays on WHP by Walter B. Mead, Gus Breytspraak, Ronald L. Hall, Dale Cannon, D.M. Yeager, J. W. Stines, Robert T. Osborn, Kieran Cashell (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - About WHP: Tradition Discovery: The Polanyi Society Periodical, Volume XXXVI, No. 2, 2009-2010: Essays on WHP by Phil Mullins, R. Melvin Keiser, Elizabeth Newman, Murray Jardine, Araminta Stone Johnston, John Berkman (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - About WHP: "William H. Poteat: A Laudatio" by R. Taylor Scott; "William Poteat: the Primacy of the Person" by David Rutledge in A ppraisal: The Journal of the Society for Post-Critical and Personalist Studies, 2008, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - About WHP: Notes, transcriptions by WBM, 1993-2008 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Material contributed by Elizabeth Newman
    - Correspondence: WHP to Elizabeth Newman, 1991-1998 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Writings of WHP: "Reflections Engendered by the Sentence: '...Central to the Biblical concept of covenant...is the notion that who we are and how we come to know restes in our bondedness with others through our words and deeds', from Elizabeth Newman's essay 'Theology and Science'" (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Material contributed by David H. Nikkel
    - Seminar handouts, including "Some Reflections", no date (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Papers written by Nikkel for Poteat seminars, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Published writings of Nikkel related to Poteat, including Radical Embodiment, Pantheism in Hartshorne and Tillich, 1995, 2008 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Material contributed by Diane Yeager
    - Poteat recommendation for Yeager NEH seminar proposal, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Material contributed by David Rutledge
    - Correspondence: WHP to David Rutledge, 1988-1995 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Writings by WHP: Sketch written for "Focus on Faculty", Duke Divinity School Review, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Material contributed by Milton Scarborough
    - Correspondence: WHP to Milton Scarborough, with explanatory note by Scarborough, 1968-1994 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Writings by WHP: "For Whom is the Real Existence of Values a Problem...", 1988 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Course-related: Notes taken by Scarborough in three graduate courses taught by WHP, with explanatory note., 1966-1969 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Scarborough's dissertation: "Erik Erikson's Anthropology and its Implications for Epistemology" (William Poteat, supervisor), 1972 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Article by Scarborough: "Mapping Poteat on the Buddha and Zen" published in Tradition and Discovery - The Polanyi Society Journal, Volume XLIV, Number 2, 2018- (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Material contributed by James W. Stines
    - Correspondence: WHP to James W. Stines, 1975-1994 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Correspondence: WHP to James W. Stiner and Samuel Watson, 1973-1993 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Correspondence: Re. book of Poteat essays, 1987, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Correspondence and papers related to yearly gatherings of former students and admirers of WHP, 1971-1975 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Course-related: "Lecture Notes: Poteat on Tragedy" by James Stines, ca. 1963 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Writings of Poteat: Dissertation, Duke University - "Pascal's Conception of Man and Modern Sensibility", pp. 1-240, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Writings of Poteat: Dissertation, Duke University - "Pascal's Conception of Man and Modern Sensibility", pp. 241-470, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Writings of Poteat: Essay - "The Body of Speech: An Essay in Linguistic Metanoia", no date (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Writings of Poteat: Review - of "Freedom and Immortality" by Ian T. Ramsey, ca. 1960 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Collected: Duke University Lectures by Michael Polanyi (hosted by WHP), 1964 (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - Collected: Dissertation supervised by WHP - "Elizabeth Sewell: Poetic Method as an Instrument of Thinking and Knowing" by Benjamin Ladner, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Material from Douglas Adams Collection at Graduate Theological Union Library, Berkeley, CA
    - Correspondence: Copies made from Doug Adams papers including to/from WHP, 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Miscellaneous copies from Adams papers, including "The Need and Plan for an Experimental College - Taken from notes by Dr. William H. Poteat", 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Writings of WHP: "Faith and Existence" The Hibbert Journal, 1953-1954 (Box 3, Folder 40)
- Audio Recordings, 1966-2008; Series II
  - Interview of WHP by James Clement van Pelt for Duke University student radio station: "A New View of Man" (1 CD), 1966 April (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Interview of WHP by James Clement van Pelt for Duke University student radio station: "A New View of Man" (2 audio tapes), 1966 April (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - WHP at Frances Marion College (1 CD), 1987 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Responses of WHP to Elizabeth Newman (and occasionally Araminta Johnston) in a graduate directed-reading course, Duke University (9 CDs), 1988 Feb-Apr (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Prof. William H. Poteat at 74 - "Some concluding thoughts and conversations with his former students" - from Polanyi Society meeting, Washington, DC (4 CDs), 1993 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Wm. Poteat / Michael Polanyi Panel Discussion; Robert Osborn re. WHP (2 CDs), 2008 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Recordings of discussions between Poteat and his graduate student Melvin Keiser (3 CDs), 1971 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Writings of Poteat, Series III
  - Bound typescript: "Polanyian Meditations: In Search of a Post Critical Logic", 1979 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Bound typescript: " Post Critical Investigations: A Philosophical Daybook", no date (Box 5, Folder 18)